Guide to the George Leslie Harrison Papers on the Federal Reserve System,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
George Leslie Harrison Papers on the Federal Reserve System,
[ca. 1920]-1940
Harrison, George Leslie, 1887-1958.
ca. 25,000 items (34 boxes, 94 v.)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078871
Biographical Note
Lawyer, financial expers. Harrison was legal secretary to Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes, 1913-1914; Assistant General Counsel, and the Counsel, Federal Reserve Board, Washington, D.C., 1914-1920; Counsel and Deputy Governor, Federal Reserve Bank of New York, 1920-1928; Governor and President of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York, 1928-1941; President, New York Life Insurance Company, 1941-1948; and Chairman of the Board, New York Life Insurance Company, 1948-1953. His career also included activities for the American Red Cross and trusteeship of Columbia University.
Scope and Content
Papers on banking and finance, especially relating to the Federal Reserve Bank of New York.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 4 series:
Series I: Binders
Series II. Files
Series III: Books
Series IV: Index
Subjects
United States.--Federal Reserve Board.; Federal Reserve Bank of New York.; American Red Cross.; Columbia University.; New York Life Insurance Company.; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1841-1935.; United States--Economic conditions.; Federal Reserve banks.; Banks and banking--United States.; Banks and banking--New York (State); Finance--United States.; Insurance companies.; Lawyers.; Financial executives.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
07/18/57 M-57-07-18 Harrison, George Leslie Gift
- Series I: Binders
  With notes by Jane Bogardus
  - Subseries I.1: S.P. Gilbert
    - S. P. Gilbert Incoming and outgoing cables between Gilbert ((Agent Gen., Reparations Payment) and various FRBNY officers, including Jay, Burgess, McGarrah, and Harrison. Many are marked "Strictly Confidential". Subjects: Reparations, B.I.S., Bank of England; dealings with J.P. Morgan and Gov. Norman, March 1926 - May1930 (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.2: Bank for International Settlements
    - Bank for International Settlements Cables; B.I.S. (mostly signed Fraser) to FRBNY; FRBNY to B.I.S.. Very few marked confidential. Subjects: B.I.S. organization and transactions; Many cables from FRBNY to B.I.S. are regular review of money market, 2 April 1930 - December 1931 (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.3: Reichsbank (Germany)
    - Reichsbank (Germany) Cables: Reichsbank to FRBNY. Marked "Confidential to Governor". Many signed by Schacht. Subjects: Transactions for accounts of Reichsbank; FRBNY series of cables on money market, 6 September 1925 - December 1930 (Box 3)
  - Subseries I.4: Bank of England
    - Bank of England Incoming and outgoing cables between Bank of England and FRBNY; many marked "Strictly Confidential for Governor"; many Bank of England signed Norman and FRBNY signed Strong. Subjects: Wide range, but mostly transactions of Bank of England with FRBNY, U .S. commercial banks, or other foreign central banks, 1922 - 1924 (Box 5)
  - Subseries I.5: Bank of France
    - Bank of France Incoming and outgoing cables between Banque de France and FRBNY; some Banque de France are marked "Confidential for Governor" and signed Moreau, Quesnay, or Rist; FRBNY signed Strong or Harrison. Subjects: Mostly Banque de France account transactions with FRBNY, U.S. commercial banks and other foreign central banks, October 1926 - March 1929 (Box 13)
  - Subseries I.6: European Trips
    - European Trips (B. Strong; P. Jay; J. E. Crane; G. L. Harrison): -- Incoming and outgoing cables; many marked "Confidential for Governor". Subjects: Business in connection with visits to foreign central banks; many cables between Governor Norman and Governor Strong concerning the condition of various European central banks, particularly the Netherlands Bank, 1926 (Box 15)
  - Subseries I.7: Officers and Others
    - Officers and Others: Federal Reserve Bank officers while abroad. [See list of names for Binder 34], 1933 - 1935 (Box 16)
  - Subseries I.8: Personal Cables
    - Personal Cables: Incoming and outgoing between McGarrah and Fraser at B. I. S. and Harrison; marked "Personal Harrison". Subjects: European financial and monetary situation, B.I .S., reparations, Young Plan, 1930 .- 1935 (Box 16)
  - Subseries I.9: Miscellaneous Cables
    - Miscellaneous Cables: Incoming and outgoing cables between 31 separate central banks (arranged alphabetically by name of bank) and FRBNY; some marked "Confidential". Subject: Account transactions with FRBNY, 1925 - 1932 (Box 17)
  - Subseries I.10: Banca D'Italia
    - Banca d'Italia Incoming and outgoing cables between this bank and FRBNY; some marked "Confidential". Subject: Account transactions with FRBNY, 1925 - 1932 (Box 19)
  - Subseries I.11: De Nederlandsche Bank
    - De Nederlandsche Bank Incoming and outgoing cables between this bank and FRBNY; some marked "Confidential". Subject: Account transactions with FRBNY, 1925 - 1932 (Box 19)
  - Subseries I.12: Swiss National Bank
    - Swiss National Bank Incoming and outgoing cables between this bank and FRBNY; some marked "Confidential". Subject: Account transactions with FRBNY, 1927 - 1932 (Box 19)
  - Subseries I.13: Banca D'Italia
    - Banca d'Italia Incoming and outgoing cables between this bank and FRBNY; some marked "Confidential". Subject: Account transactions with FRBNY, 1933 - 1938 (Box 19)
  - Subseries I.14: De Nederlandsche Bank
    - De Nederlandsche Bank Incoming and outgoing cables between this bank and FRBNY; some marked "Confidential". Subject: Account transactions with FRBNY, 1933 - 1938 (Box 20)
  - Subseries I.15: Swiss National Bank
    - Swiss National Bank Incoming and outgoing cables between this bank and FRBNY; some marked "Confidential". Subject: Account transactions with FRBNY, 1933 - 1938 (Box 20)
  - Subseries I.16: Conversations
    - Conversations: Volume I: Memos from Gov. Harrison to Confidential Files, recording telephone conversations with foreign central bankers, particularly Gov. Norman and Sir Ernest Harvey. Also Treasury officials in Washington, and others. Records of conversations with foreign central bankers while Harrison was overseas. Subjects: Wide range, but mostly concerning FRBMY bank business, including open market operations, and foreign central bank business, including Bank of England credit, 1926 - 1931 (Box 21)
  - Subseries I.17: Discussion Notes
    - Discussion Notes: Volumes I, II, & III -- Memoranda recording oral discussions concerning meeting of the FRBNY Board of Directors and the Executive Committee. Subjects: Credit policy, discount rates, purchase of Government securities, April 17, 1930 - September 21, 1933 (Box 23)
  - Subseries I.17: Discussion Notes
    - Discussion Notes: Volumes I, II, & III -- Memoranda recording oral discussions concerning meeting of the FRBNY Board of Directors and the Executive Committee. Subjects: Credit policy, discount rates, purchase of Government securities, April 17, 1930 - September 21, 1933 (Box 23)
  - Subseries I.18: Miscellaneous Letters and Reports
    - Miscellaneous Letters and Reports: Volume I -- Governor Harrison's copies of his bank correspondence, letters to Federal Reserve Board of Governors o Subjects: Mostly credit policy, discount rate, business conditions, 1920 - 1931 (Box 24)
  - Subseries I.19: Office Memoranda
    - Office Memoranda: Volume I -- Inter office memoranda between Harrison and Strong, Sproul, Burgess, etc. Also contains more memos to Confidential Files, recording telephone and verbal conversations, 1921 - 1927 (Box 26)
  - Subseries I.20: Special Memoranda
    - Special Memoranda: Volume I -- Forty-two studies that seem to be multilithed copies of special memoranda written by FRBNY officers. Most are unsigned, but some are by Burgess, Roelse, Williams. Examples: "Notes on mechanism of market for treasury bills" by Burgess (1937); "Public spending as means to recovery" by Williams (1936), 1933 - 1938 (Box 30)
  - Subseries I.21: Supplemants to the Special Memoranda
    - Supplements to the Special Memoranda (Indexed in Binders: 65 & 66): -- Section I: "Organization of the Federal Reserve System" (Box 31)
  - Subseries I.22: Governors' Conference
    - Governors Conference: Volume I -- Includes Index to Minutes, mimeographed record of meetings and decisions; from 19314 to 19140 includes the Secretary's minutes, marked "Confidential"; Volume IV includes the President's Conference, 1921 - 1926 (Box 34)
  - Subseries I.23: Federal Open Market Committee
    Minutes (multilithed) of the Executive Committee of FOMC. Some marked "Preliminary draft", some "Revised draft."
    - Volume I: Open Market Investment Committee, 1926 - 1930 (Box 35)
  - Subseries I.24: Banking Studies
    This multilithed set of spiral note books might be a pre liminary draft of the Board Banking Studies (published in 1914)
    - Vo1ume I (Box 38)
- Series II. Files
  - Answers to Questionnaire: No 7. Eligibility and Acceptability of Papers, 25 February 1931 (Box 39)
- Series III: Books
  - Books from the library of George Leslie Harrison - Inscribed and others (Box 63-73)
- Series IV: Index
  - "An Index to Correspondence and Memoranda in the George L. Harrison Papers" (Box 74)